<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!-- One method to get references from the online citation libraries.
     There has to be one entity for each item to be referenced.
     An alternate method (rfc include) is described in the references. -->

<!ENTITY RFC1034 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1034.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC1035 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.1035.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC2460 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2460.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4968 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4986.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5011 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5011.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC6781 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6781.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7626 SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7626.xml">

<!ENTITY I-D.muks-dns-message-fragments SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-muks-dns-message-fragments-00.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.wkumari-dnsop-trust-management SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-wkumari-dnsop-trust-management-01.xml">

<!ENTITY I-D.wessels-edns-key-tag SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-wessels-edns-key-tag-00.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.andrews-tcp-and-ipv6-use-minmtu SYSTEM "http://xml2rfc.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-andrews-tcp-and-ipv6-use-minmtu-04.xml">


]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs),
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocappendix="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<?rfc comments="no" ?>
<?rfc inline="yes" ?>
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-song-yeti-testbed-experience-01" ipr="trust200902">

  <front>

    <title>Experiences from Root Testbed in the Yeti DNS Project</title>

    <author fullname="Linjian Song" initials="L." surname="Song">
      <organization>Beijing Internet Institute</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2508 Room, 25th Floor, Tower A, Time Fortune</street>
          <city>Beijing</city>
          <region></region>
          <code>100028</code>
          <country>P. R. China</country>
        </postal>
        <email>songlinjian@gmail.com</email>
        <uri>http://www.biigroup.com/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Shane Kerr" initials="S." surname="Kerr">
      <organization>Beijing Internet Institute</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>2/F, Building 5, No.58 Jinghai Road, BDA</street>
          <city>Beijing</city>
          <code>100176</code>
          <country>CN</country>
        </postal>
        <email>shane@biigroup.cn</email>
        <uri>http://www.biigroup.com/</uri>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date/>

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>Internet Area</area>
    <workgroup>Internet Engineering Task Force</workgroup>

    <!-- <keyword>dns</keyword> -->

    <abstract>
      <t>This document reports and discusses issues in DNS root services,
   based on experiences from the experiments in the Yeti DNS
   project. These issues include IPv6-only operation, the root DNS
   server naming scheme, DNSSEC KSK rollover, root server renumbering,
   multiple root zone signer, and so on. This project was founded in
   May 2015 and has since built a live root DNS server system testbed
   with volunteer root server and resolver operations.</t>
    </abstract>

  </front>

  <middle>

    <section title="Introduction">
    
    <t><xref target="RFC1034"/> says the domain name space is a tree structure. 
   The top level of the tree for the unique identifier system is the DNS root system.
   It has been operational for 25+ years.  It is pivotal to making the
   current Internet useful.  So it is considered somewhat ossified for
   stability reasons.  It is hard to test and implement new ideas
   evolving to a more advanced level to counter challenges like
   IPv6-only operation, DNSSEC key/algorithm rollover<xref target="RFC4986"/>, scaling issues,
   and so on.  In order to make the test more practical, it is also
   necessary to involve users' environments which are highly
   diversified, in order to study the effect of the changes in question.</t>

    <t>To benefit Internet development as a whole, the Yeti Project was
   proposed to build a parallel, experimental, live IPv6 DNS root system
   to discover the limits of DNS root name service and deliver useful
   technical output. Possible research agenda will be explored on this
   testbed, covering several aspects (but not limited to):</t>

  <t> <list style="symbols">
  <t>IPv6-only operation</t>
  <t>DNSSEC key rollover</t>
  <t>Renumbering issues</t>
  <t>Scalability issues</t>
  <t>Multiple zone file signers</t>
  </list></t>
    <t>Starting from May 2015, three coordinators began to build this live
   experimental environment and called for participants.  At the time of
   writing, there are 14 Yeti root servers with 13 operators, and
   experimental traffic from volunteers, universities, DNS vendors,
   mirrored traffic non-Yeti traffic, and RIPE Atlas probes.  Some
   experiments have been proposed and have been verified in lab tests.</t>


  <t> Note that the Yeti DNS project has complete fealty to IANA as the DNS
   name space manager. All IANA top-level domain names will be
   precisely expressed in the Yeti DNS system, including all TLD data
   and meta-data<xref target="Root-Zone-Database"/>. So, the Yeti DNS project 
   is not an "alternative root" in the usual sense of that term. It is expected 
   to inform the IANA community by peer-reviewed science as to future possibilities to
   consider for the IANA root DNS system.</t>
  
  <t>In order to let people know the technical activities in Yeti DNS
   project, this document reports and discusses issues on root DNS
   services, based on experiences so far from the experiments in the
   Yeti DNS project.</t>

    </section>

    <section title="Problem Statement">

    <t>Some problems and policy concerns over the DNS Root Server system
   stem from centralization from the point of view of DNS content
   consumers.  These include external dependencies and surveillance
   threats.</t>

    <t><list style="symbols">
  <t>External Dependency.  Currently, there are 12 DNS Root Server
      operators for the 13 Root Server letters, with more than 500
      instances deployed globally. Yet compared to the number of
      connected devices, AS networks, and recursive DNS servers, the
      number of root instances is far from sufficient.  Connectivity
      loss between one autonomous network and the IANA root name servers
      usually results in loss of local service within the local network,
      even when internal connectivity is perfect
 </t>

  <t>Surveillance risk. Even when one or more root name server anycast
      instances are deployed locally or in a nearby network, the queries
      sent to the root servers carry DNS lookup information which
      enables root operators or other parties to analyze the DNS query
      traffic.  This is a kind of information leakage<xref target="RFC7626"/> 
      which is to some extent not acceptable to some policy makers</t>
  </list></t>

  <t>People are often told that the current root system with 13 root
   servers is not able to be extended to alleviate the above concerns,
   because it is limited to 13 by the current DNS protocol<xref target="ROOT-FAQ"/>. 
   To the best of author's knowledge, there is no scientific evidence to
   support this assertion. It remains an open question.</t>

  <t>There are some technical issues in the areas of IPv6 and DNSSEC,
   which were introduced to the DNS root server system after it was
   created. Renumbering DNS root servers also creates some technical
   issues.</t>

  <t><list style="symbols">
  <t>IPv6-only capability.  Currently some DNS servers including root which 
      support both A and AAAA (IPv4 and IPv6) records still do not respond to
      IPv6 queries.  IPv6 introduces larger IP packet MTU (1280 bytes) 
      and a different fragmentation model<xref target="RFC2460"/>.  It is not 
      clear whether DNS can survive without IPv4 (in an IPv6-only environment), 
      or what the impact of IPv6-only environment introduces to current DNS
      operations especially in the DNS root server system.</t>

  <t>KSK rollover. Currently, IANA rolls the ZSK every six weeks but
      the KSK has never been rolled as of writing.  Is the 512 bytes DNS
      packet size limitation still observed?  Is RFC5011 <xref target="RFC5011"/> widely
      supported by resolvers?  How about longer key with different
      encryption algorithm?  There are many issues still unknown.</t>

  <t>Renumbering issue. It is likely that root operators may change
      their IP addresses for root servers as well. There is no dynamic
      update mechanism to inform resolvers and other Internet
      infrastructure relying on root service of such changes.</t>
  </list></t>
    </section>
  
    <section title="Yeti Testbed and Experiment Setup">
    
    
    <t>To use the Yeti testbed operationally, the information that is
   required for correct root name service is a matching set of the
   following:</t>

  <t> <list style="symbols">
  <t>a root "hints file"</t>
  <t>the root zone apex NS record set</t>
  <t>the root zone's signing key</t>
  <t>root zone trust anchor</t>
  </list></t>
  <t>Although Yeti DNS project publishes strictly IANA information for TLD
   data and meta-data, it is necessary to use a special hint file and
   replace the apex NS RRset with Yeti authority name servers, which
   will enable the resolves to find and stick to the Yeti root system.
   In addition, unless IANA was to help Yeti sign its root zone with a
   different root set, it is necessary to use a different ZSK and
   KSK (the DNSSEC trust anchor) in Yeti system.</t>

  <t>Below is a figure to demonstrate the topology of Yeti and the basic
   data flow, which consists of the Yeti distribution master, Yeti root
   server, and Yeti resolver: </t>


  <figure>
  <artwork> 
  <![CDATA[ 

                  +------------------------+
                        |   IANA Root Zone via   |
                      +-+   F.root-servers.net   +--+
                      | +-----------+------------+  |
+-----------+         |             |               | IANA Root.Zone
|    Yeti   |         |             |               |
|  Traffic  |      +--v---+     +---v--+      +-----v+
| Collection|      |  BII |     | WIDE |      | TISF |
|           |      |  DM  |     |  DM  |      |  DM  |
+---+----+--+      +------+     +-+----+      +---+--+
    ^    ^         |              |               |
    |    |         |              |               |   Yeti Root.Zone
    |              v              v               v
         |
    |        +------+      +------+                +------+
         +- -+ Yeti |      | Yeti |   .....        | Yeti |
    |        | Root |      | Root |                | Root |
             +---+--+      +---+--+                +--+---+
    |            |             |                      |
      pcap       ^             ^                      ^ TLD lookup
    | upload     |             |                      |
     
    |                   +--------------------------+
    +- - - - - - - - - -+      Yeti Resolvers      |
                        |     (with Yeti Hint)     |
                        +--------------------------+



  ]]></artwork>
    </figure>
  <t>Figure 1. The topology of Yeti testbed</t>

    <section title="Distribution Master">

  <t>As shown in figure 1, the Yeti Root system takes the IANA root zone
   and performs minimal changes needed to serve the zone from the Yeti
   root servers instead of the IANA root servers. In Yeti, this
   modified root zone is generated by the Yeti Distribution Masters
   (DM), which provide it to the Yeti root servers.</t>

  <t>So the generation process is: </t>
  <t> <list style="symbols">
  <t>DM downloads the latest IANA root zone at a certain time</t>
  <t>DM makes modifications to change from the IANA to Yeti root servers</t>
  <t>DM signs the new Yeti root zone</t>
  <t>DM publishes the new Yeti root zone to Yeti root servers</t>
  </list></t>
  <t>While in principle this could be done by a single DM, Yeti uses a set
   of three DMs to avoid any sense that the Yeti project is run by a
   single organization.  The three Distribution Masters (DMs) can
   independently fetch the root zone from IANA, sign it and publish the
   latest zone data to Yeti root servers.</t>

  <t>In the same while, these DMs coordinate their work so that the
   resulting Yeti root zone is always consistent.  There are two aspects
   of coordination between three DMs: timing and information
   synchronization.</t>

  <section title="Yeti root zone SOA SERIAL">

   <t>Consistency with IANA root zone except the top level apex record is 
    one of most important point for the project. As part of Yeti DM design, 
    the Yeti SOA SERIAL which reflect the changes of yeti root zone is one 
    factor to be considered. </t>

    <t>Currently IANA SOA SERIAL number for root zone is in the form of 
    YYYYMMDDNN, like 2015111801. In Yeti root system, IANA SOA SERIAL is 
    directly copied in to Yeti SOA SERIAL. So once the IANA root zone has changed 
    with a new SOA SERIAL, a new version of the Yeti root zone is generated 
    with the same SOA SERIAL.</t>

    <t>There is a case of Yeti DM operation that when a new Yeti root server 
added, DM operator change the Yeti root zone without change the SOA SERIAL 
 which introduces inconsistency of Yeti root system. To avoid inconsistency, 
the DMs hold on every changes to Yeti apex record and only new IANA SOA 
SERIAL will trigger the operation of adding these changes to Yeti root zone.</t>

    <t>A analysis of IANA convention shows IANA SOA SERIAL change 2 times every day 
      (NN=00, 01). And that since October 2007 the maximum of NN was 03 while 13 times 
     it is observed that the versions with NN=02. So in the worst case, the changes 
     of Yeti apex record is updated into Yeti root zone in less than 12 hours.
   </t>

  </section>

  <section title="Timing of Root Zone Fetch">
  <t>Yeti root system operators do not receive notify message from IANA
   when IANA root zone updates with a new SOA serial number.  So Yeti DMs
   check the root zone periodically. At the time of writing, each Yeti
   DM checks to see if the IANA root zone has changed hourly, on the
   following schedule:</t>

    <texttable>

    <ttcol>DM Operator</ttcol>
    <ttcol>Time</ttcol>
    <c>BII</c><c>hour+00</c>
    <c>WIDE</c><c>hour+20</c>
    <c>TISF</c><c>hour+40</c>
  </texttable>
   <t>
   Note that Yeti DMs can check IANA root zone more frequently (every minute 
   for example). A test done by Yeti participant shows that the delay of IANA root zone
   update from the first IANA root server to last one is around 20 minute.
   Once a Yeti DM fetch the new root zone, it will notify all the Yeti root 
   server with a new SOA serial number. So normally yeti root server will be 
   notified in less than 20 minute after new IANA root zone generated. Ideally, 
   if IANA DM notifies the Yeti DMs, Yeti root zone will be updated more timely.
 
   </t>
  </section>

    <section title="Information Synchronization">

  <t>Given three DMs operational in Yeti root system, it is necessary to
   prevent any inconsistency caused by human mistakes in operation.  The
   straight method is to share the same parameters to produce the Yeti
   root zone.  There parameters includes following set of files: </t>

    <t> <list style="symbols">
    <t>the list of Yeti root servers, including:
      <list style="symbols">
      <t>public IPv6 address and host name </t>
      <t>IPv6 addresses originating zone transfer</t>
      <t>IPv6 addresses to send DNS notify to</t>
      </list></t>
    <t>the ZSKs used to sign the root</t>
    <t>the KSK used to sign the root</t>
    <t>the SERIAL when this information is active</t>
  </list></t>

  <t>The theory of operation is that each DM operator runs a Git
   repository, containing files with the information needed to produce
   the Yeti root zone.  When a change is desired (such as adding a new
   server or rolling the ZSK), a DM operator updates the local Git
   repository.  A SOA SERIAL in the future is chosen for when the
   changes become active.  The DM operator then pushes the changes to
   the Git repositories of the other two DM operators.  When the SOA SERIAL
   of the root zone passes the number chosen, then the new version of
   the information is used.</t>
    </section>
  </section>
      
      <section title="Yeti Root Servers">

      <t> In Yeti Root system, authoritative servers donated and operated by
   Yeti volunteers are configured as a slave to the Yeti DM.  As the
   time of writing, there are 14 Yeti root servers distributed around
   the world.  As one of operational research goal, all authoritative
   servers are required to work in an IPv6-only environment. In addition,
   until the IANA root, Yeti root server only serve the Yeti root zone, 
   other than root-servers.org zone and .arpa zone.</t>

          <figure>
  <artwork> 
    <![CDATA[
.                              3600000    IN   NS       bii.dns-lab.net                         
bii.dns-lab.net                3600000    IN   AAAA     240c:f:1:22::6                          
.                              3600000    IN   NS       yeti-ns.tisf.net                        
yeti-ns.tisf.net               3600000    IN   AAAA     2001:559:8000::6                        
.                              3600000    IN   NS       yeti-ns.wide.ad.jp                      
yeti-ns.wide.ad.jp             3600000    IN   AAAA     2001:200:1d9::35                        
.                              3600000    IN   NS       yeti-ns.as59715.net                     
yeti-ns.as59715.net            3600000    IN   AAAA     2a02:cdc5:9715:0:185:5:203:53           
.                              3600000    IN   NS       dahu1.yeti.eu.org                       
dahu1.yeti.eu.org              3600000    IN   AAAA     2001:4b98:dc2:45:216:3eff:fe4b:8c5b     
.                              3600000    IN   NS       ns-yeti.bondis.org                      
ns-yeti.bondis.org             3600000    IN   AAAA     2a02:2810:0:405::250                    
.                              3600000    IN   NS       yeti-ns.ix.ru                           
yeti-ns.ix.ru                  3600000    IN   AAAA     2001:6d0:6d06::53                       
.                              3600000    IN   NS       yeti.bofh.priv.at                       
yeti.bofh.priv.at              3600000    IN   AAAA     2a01:4f8:161:6106:1::10                 
.                              3600000    IN   NS       yeti.ipv6.ernet.in                      
yeti.ipv6.ernet.in             3600000    IN   AAAA     2001:e30:1c1e:1::333                    
.                              3600000    IN   NS       yeti-dns01.dnsworkshop.org              
yeti-dns01.dnsworkshop.org     3600000    IN   AAAA     2001:1608:10:167:32e::53                
.                              3600000    IN   NS       yeti-ns.conit.co                        
yeti-ns.conit.co               3600000    IN   AAAA     2607:ff28:2:10::47:a010                 
.                              3600000    IN   NS       dahu2.yeti.eu.org                       
dahu2.yeti.eu.org              3600000    IN   AAAA     2001:67c:217c:6::2                      
.                              3600000    IN   NS       yeti.aquaray.com                        
yeti.aquaray.com               3600000    IN   AAAA     2a02:ec0:200::1                         
.                              3600000    IN   NS       yeti-ns.switch.ch                       
yeti-ns.switch.ch              3600000    IN   AAAA     2001:620:0:ff::29    
  ]]>
  </artwork>
</figure>
<t>Figure 2. the Yeti root server in hint file </t>

      <t>Since Yeti is a scientific research project, it needs to capture DNS
   traffic sent for later analysis.  Today some servers use dnscap,
   which is a DNS-specific tool to produce pcap files.  There are
   several versions of dnscap floating around; some people use the
   Verisign one.  Since dnscap loses packets in some cases (tested on a
   Linux kernel), some people use pcapdump.  It requires the patch
   attached to this bug report <xref target="dnscap-bug-report"/></t>

      <t>System diversity is also a requirement and observed for current 14
   Yeti root server. Here are the results of a survey regarding the
   machine, operation system and DNS software:
      </t>
    <t> <list style="symbols">
        <t>Machine: 11 out of 14 root server operator are using a VPS to
      provide service. </t>
        <t>OS: 6 operators use Linux (including Ubuntu, Debian, CentOS). 5
      operators use FreeBSD and 1 NetBSD. 2 other servers are unknown.</t>
        <t>DNS software: 8 our of 14 root server use BIND (varying from 9.9.7
      to 9.10.3). 4 of them use NSD (4.10 and 4.15). The other 2 servers
      use Knot (2.0.1 and 2.1.0).</t>
      </list></t>
    </section>
      
      <section title="Yeti Resolvers and Experimental Traffic" >

      <t>In client side of Yeti project,  there are DNS resolvers with IPv6 
      support, updated with Yeti “hints” file to use the Yeti root servers instead 
      of the IANA root servers and using Yeti KSK as trust anchor. Since the 
      DNSSEC key of the Yeti root (the KSK) changes often (typically every three 
      months), it is required that resolver operator to configure your resolver 
      compliant to RFC 5011 for automatic update. For Yeti resolver, it is also
      Interesting to try some mechanism end-system resolvers to signal to a server 
      about their DNSSEC key status, like <xref target="I-D.wessels-edns-key-tag"/> 
      and <xref target="I-D.wkumari-dnsop-trust-management"/> mentioned.</t>

      <t>Participants and volunteers are expected from individual researchers, 
        labs of universities, companies and institutes, and vendors (for 
        example, the DNS software implementers), developers of CPE devices 
        &amp; IoT devices, and middle box developers who can test their 
        product and connect their own testbed into Yeti testbed. Resolvers 
        donated by Yeti volunteers are required to be configured with Yeti 
        hint file and Yeti DNSSEC KSK.  It is required that Yeti resolver 
        can speak both IPv4 and IPv6, given that not all the stub resolver 
        and authoritative servers on the Internet are IPv6 capable. </t>

      <t>At the time of writing several universities and labs have joined us
   and contributed certain amount of traffic to Yeti testbed. But it is
   far from the desired volume of experiment traffic. So Yeti adopts two
   alternative ways to increase the experimental traffic in the Yeti testbed
   and check the functionality of Yeti root system.</t>

      <t>One approach is to mirror the real traffic by off-path method and
   reply it into Yeti testbed; this is implemented by one of the Yeti
   root server operators. Another approach is to use some traffic
   generating tool such as RIPE Atlas probes to generate specific
   queries against Yeti servers.</t>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title="Experiments in Yeti Testbed">
      
      <t> The main goal of Yeti DNS Project is to act as an experimental
   network. Experiments will be conducted on this network.  In order
   to make the findings that result from these experiments more
   rigorous, an experiment protocol is proposed.</t>

      <t>A Yeti experiment goes through four phases:</t>
        <t> <list style="symbols">
      <t>Proposal. The first step is to make a proposal. It is discussed and if accepted 
        by the Yeti participants then it can proceed to the next phase.</t>

       <t>Lab Test. The next phase is to run a version of the experiment in a controlled 
        environment. The goal is to check for problems such as software crashes or protocol 
        errors that may cause failures on the Yeti network, before putting onto the 
        experimental network. </t>

       <t>Yeti Test. The next phase actually running the experiment on the Yeti network. 
        Details of this will depend on the experiment. It must be coordinated with the Yeti 
        participants.</t>

       <t>Report of Findings. When completed, a report of the findings of the experiment 
        should be made. It need not be an extensive document. </t>
      </list></t>
       <t> In this section, we are going to introduce some experiments implemented and 
        planned in Yeti project.</t>

      <section title="Naming Scheme and Glue Issue">
    
      <t>In root server history, the naming scheme for individual root servers
   was not fixed.  Current IANA Root server adopt [a-m].root-servers.net
   to represent 13 servers which are labeled with letter from A to M.
   For example, L root operated by ICANN uses l.root-servers.net to
   represent their server as NS.  One reason behind this naming scheme
   is that the common suffix 'root-servers.net' can be compressed in DNS
   message to produce a smaller DNS response.</t>

      <t>Different from the IANA root naming scheme, the Yeti root system uses
   separate and normal domains for root servers (shown in figure 2).
   The motivation of this naming scheme in Yeti is that it intentionally
   produces larger packets for priming responses. Note that currently, the Yeti 
   root has a priming response which is almost the same size as the IANA root. 
   Yeti has no compression, and has one more name server, but it also has no 
   IPv4 addresses.</t>

   <t>the change of name scheme not only affects the size of priming response, but also
   changes the content in additional section of the response.When a resolver bootstraps, 
   it sends a 'NS-for-dot' query to one of
   the root servers that it knows about, which is called a priming
   query.  It looks like this with the "dig" command:</t>

      <t>$ dig @a.root-servers.net -t ns +norecurse +edns +nodnssec </t>

      <t>Normally in the IANA root system the priming response contains the
   _names_ of the root servers in the answer section and the _addresses_
   of the root servers in the additional section.  The additional
   section data is what the resolvers need to actually perform
   recursion.  Shown as below: </t>
          <figure>
  <artwork> 
    <![CDATA[
In priming response : 

Answer Section: 
---------------
.        518400  IN  NS  a.root-servers.net.
.        518400  IN  NS  b.root-servers.net.
  ...
.        518400  IN  NS  m.root-servers.net.

Addtional section: 
------------------
a.root-servers.net.     3600000  IN  A 198.41.0.4
b.root-servers.net.     3600000  IN  A 192.228.79.201
  ...
m.root-servers.net.     3600000  IN  AAAA  2001:dc3::35

          ]]>
  </artwork>
</figure>
      <t>In IANA root system, all the root server returns the "a.root-
   servers.net" addresses in the additional section, because root
   servers not only answer for root zone, but also answer for "root-
   servers.net" zone.  Note that BIND will not behave like this if it is
   not configured for the "root-servers.net" zone.  NSD and Knot happily
   return such "glue" in the additional section, whether configured for
   the "root-servers.net" zone or not.</t>
    
      <t>The Yeti root naming scheme uses separate and independent domain for
   individual root servers.  It this case, the priming response from
   Yeti root servers will only contain the A &amp; AAAA records of that
   responding server in BIND 9.  However it is desired that the Yeti root servers
   respond to priming queries with the addresses of all Yeti root
   servers in the additional section.  This will make them operate as
   similar to the IANA root servers as possible.</t>

      <t>In Yeti root system, there are two approaches adopted in different
   root servers.  One is to patch BIND 9 so that it includes the glue
   addresses in the additional section.  The other one is to add a zone
   file for each root server and answer for all of them at each Yeti
   server.  That means each Yeti root server would have a small zone
   file for "bii.dns-lab.net", "yeti-ns.wide.ad.jp", "yeti-ns.tisf.net",
   and so on.</t>

      </section>
      <section title="Multiple-Signers with Multi-ZSK">
  

      <t>According to the Problem statement of Yeti DNS project, more
   independent participants and operators of root system is desirable.
   As the name implies, multi-ZSK mode will introduce different ZSKs 
   sharing a single unique KSK, as opposed to the IANA root system
   (which uses a single ZSK to sign the root zone).  On the condition of
   good availability and consistency on root system, the Multi-ZSK
   proposal is designed to give each DM operator enough room to manage
   their own ZSK, by choosing different ZSK, length, duration, and so
   on; even the encryption algorithm may vary.</t>

      <t> According to the Yeti experiment protocol, a lab test was done to
   verify the concept and validity of Multi-ZSK.  The purpose of the
   test is two-fold: 1) To test whether this proposal can be implemented
   by current DNS protocol &amp; software (to see if there should be some
   extra modification to protocol or software), and 2) To demonstrate
   the impact of Multi-ZSK proposal to the current root system.</t>

       <t>The experiment is run like this: build a test topology like figure 3,
   with 2 Root servers and a resolver (BIND 9).  The hint file of this
   test only contains the two DM servers.  In the first time slot, Root
   A is up and Root B is turned off.  Let resolver bootstrap from Root A
   and query a certain signed TLD (or a junk query).  For the second time
   slot, turn off Root A and turn on Root B.  Let resolver shift to Root
   B to look up another TLD (or a junk query). The test result of different
   time slot is compared to see whether the resolver can validate the DNSSEC
   signature.</t>
  
            <figure>
  <artwork> 
    <![CDATA[
+---------------+          +---------------+  
|    Root A     |          |     Root B    |  
|   (ZSK A)     |          |     (ZSK B)   |  
+-------+-------+          +--------+------+  
        |                           |        
--------+------------+--------------+--------                       
                     |                        
           +---------+----------+             
           |                    |                      
           |     Resolver       |                        
           +--------------------+  
          ]]>
  </artwork>
</figure>
<t>Figure 3. Multi-ZSK lab test topology</t>

      <t>There are two cases in this test:</t>
<t> <list style="symbols">
      <t>Case 1: Assign one ZSK to the smart sign process on each DM, which 
        means the root zone only contain one single ZSK.</t>

      <t>Case 2: Assign both ZSK A and ZSK B to the smart sign process on
      each DM, which means the root zone contains two ZSK.  In this case,
      it is required that Root A and Root B to share their public ZSK to
      each other before root zone is signed.</t>
</list></t>

    <t>In case 1 SERVFAIL is received during switching because the resolver
   can not validate the signature signed by Root B after switching.  In
   case 2 NOERROR is received.  It is the actual demonstration of how
   Multi-ZSK works by adding multiple ZSK to the root zone.  As a
   result, the resolver will cache the key sets instead of single ZSK to
   validate the data no matter it is signed by Root A or Root B.  As
   follow-up test, Unbound also passed the test with more than 10 DMs
   and 10 ZSKs.</t>
    
      <t> Although more DM and ZSK can be added into the test, adding more ZSKs
   to root zone enlarges the DNS response size for DNSKEY queries
   which may be a concern given the limitation of DNS packet size.
   Current IANA root server operators are inclined to keep the packets
   size as small as possible.  So the number of DM and ZSK will be
   parameter which is decided based on operation experience.  In the
   current Yeti root testbed, there will be 3 DMs, each with a separate
   ZSK.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Root Renumbering Issue and Hint File Update">
    <t> With the nearing renumbering of H root Server's IP address, there is
   a discussion of ways that resolvers can update their hint file.
   Traditional ways include using FTP protocol by doing a wget and
   using dig to get the servers' addresses manually.  Each way would
   depend on operators manual operation.  As a result, there are many
   old machines that have not updated their hint files.  As a proof,
   after done renumbering for thirteen years, there is an observation
   that the "Old J-Root" can still receive DNS query traffic <xref target="Renumbering-J-Root"/>.</t>

    <t>This experiment proposal aims to find an automatic way for hint-file
   updating.  The already-completed work is a shell script tool which
   provides the function that update a hint-file in file system
   automatically with DNSSEC and trust anchor validation.</t>

    <t>The methodology is straightforward.  The tool first queries the NS
   list for "." domain and queries A and AAAA record for every domain on
   the NS list.  It requires DNSSEC validation for both signature and
   trust anchor for all the answers.  After getting all the answers, the
   tool compares the new hint file to the old one.  If there is a
   difference, it renames the old one with a time-stamp and replaces the
   old one with the new one.  Otherwise the tool deletes the new hint
   file and nothing will be changed.</t>

    <t>Note that in current IANA root system the servers named in the root
   NS record are not signed due to lack of incentive.  So the tool can
   not fully work in the production network.  In Yeti root system some
   of the names listed in the NS record are signed, which provides a
   test environment for such a proposal.</t>

      </section>
      <section title="DNS Fragments">

      <t>In consideration of new DNS protocol and operation, there is always a
   hard limit on the DNS packet size.  Take Yeti for example: adding
   more root servers, using the Yeti naming scheme, rolling the KSK, and
   Multi-ZSK increase the packet size.  The fear of large DNS packets
   mainly stem from two aspects: one is IP-fragments and the other is
   frequently falling back to TCP.</t>

      <t>In Yeti testbed, a mechanism is implemented which supports larger DNS
   packet working around the IP-layer fragment caused by middle box
   misbehavior (in IPv4) and IPv6 MTU limitation by splitting a single
   DNS message across multiple UDP datagrams.  This DNS fragments
   mechanism is documented in <xref target="I-D.muks-dns-message-fragments"/> as an
   experimental IETF draft.</t>

      </section>

      <section title="The KSK Rollover Experiment in Yeti">
      
        <t>The Yeti project provides a good basis to conduct a real-world
   experiment of a root KSK roll. It is not a perfect analogy to the
   IANA root because all of the resolvers to the Yeti experiment are
   "opt-in", and are presumably run by administrators who are interested
   in the DNS and knowledgeable about it. Still, it can inform the IANA
   root KSK roll.</t>

        <t>The IANA root KSK has not been rolled.  ICANN put together a design
   team to analyze the problem and make recommendations.  The design
   team put together a proposal<xref target="ICANN-ROOT-ROLL"/>. Whether this proposal
   or a different one is adopted, the Yeti project can use it as a basis
   for an experimental KSK roll.  The experiment may not be identical,
   since the time-lines laid out in the current IANA plan are very long,
   and the Yeti project would like to conduct the experiment in a
   shorter time.</t>

        <t>The Yeti project would also like to conduct an experiment to try
   rolling the root KSK using a straightforward method, such as a
   double-DS approach outlined in <xref target="RFC6781"/>. If this ends up being
   adopted for the IANA root, then only a single Yeti experiment will
   need to be conducted.</t>
 
      <t>&lt; &lt;  It‘s worthwhile to mention that in Yeti testbed there is a 
        lesson when the KSK rollover was implemented at the first time. It lasted for one 
        month and has been held off afterwards. In the first trial, it make old KSK inactive 
        in one week after new key created, and delete it in another week, which 
        is totally unaware of RFC5011. Because the hold-down timer is not correctly 
        set in the server side, some clients(unbound) SERVFAILs (like dig 
        without +cd) because the new key is still in AddPend state when old key is 
        inactive . The lesson from the first KSK trial is that both 
        server and client should compliant to RFC5011 to set proper timer. The 
        question is how can authority server know the resolver is ready for RFC5011？
        some drafts <xref target="I-D.wessels-edns-key-tag"/> and 
        <xref target="I-D.wkumari-dnsop-trust-management"/> try to address the problem.
        &gt;&gt;
        </t>

      </section>  
    </section>

    <section title="Other Technical findings and bugs">
      <t>Besides the experiments with specific goal and procedures, some
   unexpected bugs have been reported.  It is worthwhile to record them
   as technical findings from Yeti DNS Project. Hopefully, these
   experiences can share and help. </t>

      <section title="IPv6 fragments issue"> 
      <t>
        There are two cases in Yeti testbed reported that some Yeti root
   servers on VPS failed to pull the zone from Distribution Master via
   AXFR/IXFR. Two facts have been revealed in both client side and
   server side after trouble shooting.</t>

      <t>One fact in client side is that some operation system on VPS can not
   handle IPv6 fragments correctly which causes failure when they are
   doing AXRF/IXFR in TCP.  The bug covers several OS and one VM
   platform (listed below).</t>

    <texttable>
    <ttcol>OS</ttcol>
    <ttcol>VM</ttcol>
    <c>NetBSD 6.1 and 7.0RC1</c><c>VMware ESXI 5.5</c>
    <c>FreeBSD10.0 </c><c> </c>
    <c>Debian 3.2</c><c> </c>
    </texttable>

      <t>Another fact is from server side in which one TCP segment of AXRF/
   IXFR is fragmented in IP layer resulting in two fragmented packets.
   This weird behavior has been documented IETF draft<xref target="I-D.andrews-tcp-and-ipv6-use-minmtu"/>. 
   It reports a situation that some implementations of TCP running over IPv6 
   neglect to check the IPV6_USE_MIN_MTU value when performing MSS negotiation 
   and when constructing a TCP segment.  It will cause TCP MSS option set to 1440
   bytes, but IP layer will limit the packet less than 1280 bytes and
   fragment the packets which finally result two fragmented packets.</t>

        <t>The latter is not a technical error though, but it will cause the
   error in the former fact which deserves much attention in IPv6
   operation when VPS is already widely used.
        </t>
        </section>

      <section title="Root compression issue"> 
       <t><xref target="RFC1035"/>specifies DNS massage compression scheme which allows a
       domain name in a message to be represented as either: 1) a sequence
       of labels ending in a zero octet, 2) a pointer, 3) or a sequence of
       labels ending with a pointer.  It is designed to save more room of
       DNS packet. </t>

        <t>However in Yeti testbed, it is  found that Knot 2.0 server compresses even the
          root.  It means in a DNS message the name of root (a zero octet) is
          replaced by a pointer of 2 octets.  As well, it is legal but breaks
          some tools (Go DNS lib in this bug report) which does not expect such
           name compression for root.  Now both Knot and Go DNS lib have fixed
           that bug.
        </t>

          </section>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This document requires no action from the IANA.</t>
    
    </section>

      <section title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>
      The editors fully acknowledge that this memo is based on works and discussions with 
      Paul Vixie and Akira Kato in Yeti DNS project<xref target="Yeti-DNS-Project"/>. 
      Thanks to Antonio Prado and Stephane Bortzmeyer who helped to review the document 
      and give many editing suggestions</t>

      <t>Acknowledgment to all the Yeti participant and volunteers who make the experimental testbed 
      become functional and workable. </t>
    
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>

    <references title="References">
      &RFC1034;&RFC1035;&RFC2460;&RFC6781;&RFC4968;&RFC7626;&RFC5011;
      &I-D.muks-dns-message-fragments;&I-D.wkumari-dnsop-trust-management;
      &I-D.andrews-tcp-and-ipv6-use-minmtu;&I-D.wessels-edns-key-tag;

    <reference anchor="Renumbering-J-Root" target="https://indico.dns-oarc.net/event/24/session/10/contribution/10/material/slides/0.pdf">
              <front>
                  <title>Thirteen Years of “Old J-Root”</title>
      <author fullname="Duane Wessels"  initials="D." surname="Wessels"></author>
      <date year="2015" />            
              </front>
     </reference>
     <reference anchor="Root-Zone-Database" target="http://www.iana.org/domains/root/db">
            <front>
                <title>Root Zone Database</title>
                <author ></author>
                <date />
            </front>
     </reference>
         <reference anchor="ICANN-ROOT-ROLL" target="https://www.icann.org/en/system/files/files/root-zone-ksk-rollover-plan-draft-04aug15-en.pdf">
            <front>
                <title>Root Zone KSK Rollover Plan</title>
                <author ></author>
                <date year="2015" /> 
            </front>
     </reference>
     <reference anchor="ROOT-FAQ" target="https://www.isoc.org/briefings/020/">
          <front>
                  <title>DNS Root Name Server FAQ</title>
      <author fullname="Daniel Karrenberg"  initials="D." surname="Karrenberg"></author>
      <date year="2007" />            
    </front>
  </reference>
       <reference anchor="dnscap-bug-report" target="https://bugs.debian.org/cgi-bin/bugreport.cgi?bug=545985">
            <front>
                <title>pcaputils: IWBN to have an option to run a program after file rotation in pcapdump </title>
                <author fullname="Stephane Bortzmeyer"  initials="S." surname="Bortzmeyer"></author>
                <date year="2009" />
            </front>
     </reference>
     <reference anchor="Yeti-DNS-Project" target="http://www.yeti-dns.org">
            <front>
                <title>Website of Yeti DNS Project</title>
                <author ></author>
                <date />
            </front>
     </reference>
    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>

